<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="inputfd_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2017 © Red Hat, Inc.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
    obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files
    (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction,
    including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge,
    publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software,
    and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so,
    subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the
    next paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial
    portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
    NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
    BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN
    ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN
    CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
    SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Wayland protocol for direct fd access to input devices">
    This description provides a high-level overview of the interfaces
    in this protocol. For details, see the protocol specification.

    Some input devices do not interact with the windowing system. Examples
    of such input devices are gaming controllers or 3D mice. In many cases,
    a client requires direct access to the device to access or interpret
    device-specific functionality.

    This interface provides client access to input devices via a file
    descriptor (fd). The compositor may restrict the type of device
    accessible and it may restrict specific events from being sent to the
    client (e.g.  by masking the Home button on a gamepad). Otherwise, a
    client should treat the device as if opened manually.

    Multiple input devices may exists and be assigned to different seats.
    The top-level object of this protocol is a wp_inputfd_manager. A client
    must request the desired interface for a given seat. This object then
    provides the list of devices for that category that match the fd type of
    that interface. At the moment, only the evdev fd type is supported but in
    the future, a device may be accessible via multiple fd interfaces.

    Once a compositor deems a device to be focused on the client or on a
    client's surface it sends a focus_in event with a file descriptor for
    this device. A compositor may arbitrarily revoke access
    to the device by sending a wp_inputfd.focus_out. Additionally, a
    compositor may invoke system functionality to restrict access to the
    file descriptor, e.g. by using EVIOCREVOKE on an evdev fd.

    Otherwise, a client should treat the file descriptor as direct access to
    the device for the duration of it having access.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and
    backward incompatible changes may be made. Backward compatible changes
    may be added together with the corresponding interface version bump.
    Backward incompatible changes are done by bumping the version number in
    the protocol and interface names and resetting the interface version.
    Once the protocol is to be declared stable, the 'z' prefix and the
    version number in the protocol and interface names are removed and the
    interface version number is reset.
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_inputfd_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="controller object for direct fd access input devices">
      An object that provides access to the input devices available for
      direct fd access on this system. All input devices are associated with
      a seat, to get access to the actual devices use
      wp_inputfd_manager.get_seat_evdev.
    </description>

    <request name="get_seat_evdev">
      <description summary="get the evdev seat for receiving device notifications">
	Get the wp_inputfd_seat_evdev object for the given seat. This object
	provides access to all exposed devices in this seat via
	evdev-compatible file descriptors.

	The decision which device is available through this interface is
	made by the compositor. The protocol makes no guarantees whether a
	specific device is available through this interface.
      </description>
      <arg name="inputfd_seat" type="new_id" interface="wp_inputfd_seat_evdev_v1"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="The wl_seat object to retrieve the input devices for" />
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the memory for the inputfd manager object">
	Destroy the wp_inputfd_manager object. Objects created from this
	object are unaffected and should be destroyed separately.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_inputfd_seat_evdev_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="controller object for input devices of a seat">
      An object that provides access to the input devices available on this
      seat via an evdev-compatible file descriptor. After binding to this
      interface, the compositor immediately sends a set of
      wp_inputfd_seat_evdev.device_added events for currently available
      devices and later whenever a new device becomes available.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the memory for the inputfd seat object">
	Destroy the wp_inputfd_seat_evdev object. Objects created from this
	object are unaffected and should be destroyed separately.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="device_added">
      <description summary="new device notification">
	This event is sent whenever a new device becomes available on
	this seat. This event only provides the object id of the devices,
	any static information about the device (device name,
	vid/pid, etc.) is sent through the wp_inputfd_device_evdev interface.

	Which devices are compatible input devices for this seat is a
	decision made by the compositor, the protocol makes no guarantee
	that any specific device becomes available to a client.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_inputfd_device_evdev_v1"
	summary="the newly added device"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_inputfd_device_evdev_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="evdev-compatible inputfd device">
      The wp_inputfd_device_evdev interface represents one device node
      in the Linux kernel evdev interface. The fd passed to the client
      supports the ioctls and read/write commands of that interface. The
      protocol makes no guarantees which ioctls are available on the fd,
      this decision is made by the kernel.

      A device has a number of static characteristics, e.g. device
      name and pid/vid. These capabilities are sent in an event sequence
      immediately after the wp_inputfd_seat.device_added event. This initial
      event sequence is terminated by a wp_inputfd_device_evdev.done event. This
      sequence is sent only once and always before the first
      wp_inputfd_device.focus_in event.

      A device is the representation of a logical device as exposed by the
      underlying system and may only represent parts of a single physical
      input device. It is the client's task to identify the device as part
      of a physical device and to group the logical devices together as
      appropriate.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the inputfd object">
	This destroys the client's resource for this inputfd object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="name">
      <description summary="device name">
	The name is a UTF-8 encoded string with the device's name, intended
	for presentation to the user.

	This event is sent in the initial burst of events before the
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.done event.

	This event is optional, if the required information is not available
	for this device the event is omitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="the device name"/>
    </event>

    <event name="usb_id">
      <description summary="device USB vendor/product id">
	This event is sent in the initial burst of events before the
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.done event.

	This event is optional, if the required information is not available
	for this device the event is omitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="vid" type="uint" summary="USB vendor id"/>
      <arg name="pid" type="uint" summary="USB product id"/>
    </event>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="device description events sequence complete">
	This event is sent immediately to signal the end of the initial
	burst of descriptive events. A client may consider the static
	description of the device to be complete and finalize
	initialization of the device.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="device removed event">
	Sent when the device has been removed from the system.

	If the client currently has the device focus, a
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.focus_out event is sent before the removed
	event. See wp_inputfd_device.focus_in for more details.

	When this event is received, the client must
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.destroy the object.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="focus_in">
      <description summary="input fd device focus in event">
	Notification that this client now has the focus and/or access to
	this device. How focus is set is left to the
	compositor. For example, a compositor may tie joystick focus to the
	wl_pointer focus of this seat. The protocol does not guarantee that
	any specific client ever receives the focus for a device.

	The client is passed a file descriptor with access to this
	device. This file descriptor is valid until a subsequent
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.focus_out event. Upon
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.focus_out, the compositor may revoke the fd
	and further operations will fail.

	However, due to potential race conditions a client must be able to
	handle errors as if it opened the fd itself. No guarantee is given
	that the wp_inputfd_device_evdev.focus_out event or
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.removed event are sent before the client
	encounters an error on the file descriptor.

	A compositor guarantees the file descriptor for a
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev refers to the same kernel device after each
	focus_in event. In other words, any constant information about the
	device obtained through the fd (e.g. the EVIOCGPROP ioctl) is
	the same after each focus in event. Thus, a client needs to do so
	only once at the first focus_in. This guarantee does not extend to
	information that the kernel may change at runtime (e.g. the
	EVIOCGABS ioctl).

	If applicable, this event contains the surface that has the focus.
	In some cases, the focus may not be tied to a specific client surface
	but is given to the client independent of any surface. In that case,
	the surface is null.

	The protocol guarantees that focus_in and focus_out always come in
	pairs. If the client currently has the focus and the device is
	removed, a focus_out event is sent to the client before the
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.removed event.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="fd" type="fd" summary="file descriptor to the device"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
	summary="The current surface that has the device's focus" allow-null="true"/>
    </event>

    <event name="focus_out">
      <description summary="input fd device focus out event">
	Notification that this client no longer has focus and/or access to
	this device. Further reads from this device's file descriptor
	may fail. The client must close(2) the file descriptor received in
	the wp_inputfd_device_evdev.focus_in event.

	This event does not mean the device was removed, merely that the
	device is focused elsewhere. For device removal, see
	wp_inputfd_device_evdev.removed.

	See wp_inputfd_device_evdev.focus_in for more details.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
