<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_blur_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (C) 2015 Martin Gräßlin
    Copyright (C) 2015 Marco Martin
    Copyright (C) 2020 Vlad Zahorodnii
    Copyright (C) 2024 Xaver Hugl

    This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
    it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
    the Free Software Foundation, either version 2.1 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
    along with this program.  If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="ext_blur_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="blur object factory">
      This protocol provides a way to improve visuals of translucent surfaces
      by blurring background behind them.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the blur manager object">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer be using this
        protocol object. Existing objects created by this object are not
        affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="blur_exists" value="0"
             summary="the surface has already a blur object associated"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_blur">
      <description summary="get a blur object">
        Instantiate an interface extension for the given wl_surface to
        blur background behind it. If the given wl_surface already has
        a ext_blur_surface_v1 object associated, the blur_exists protocol
        error will be raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_blur_surface_v1"
           summary="the new ext_blur_surface_v1 object"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_blur_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="blur object for a surface">
      The blur object provides a way to specify a region behind a surface
      that should be blurred by the compositor.

      If the wl_surface associated with the ext_blur_surface_v1 object has been
      destroyed, this object becomes inert.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the blur object">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer be using this
        protocol object. The blur region will be unset on the next commit.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_region">
      <description summary="set blur region">
        This request sets the region of the surface that will have its
        background blurred.

        The blur region is specified in the surface-local coordinates.

        The initial value for the blur region is empty. Setting the pending
        blur region has copy semantics, and the wl_region object can be
        destroyed immediately. A NULL wl_region causes the blur region to be
        set to infinite.

        The blur region is double-buffered state, and will be applied on
        the next wl_surface.commit.

        The blur algorithm is subject to compositor policies.
      </description>
      <arg name="region" type="object" interface="wl_region" allow-null="true"
           summary="blur region of the surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
