<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="surface_invalidation_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2022 Simon Ser

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="surface invalidation">
    This protocol allows compositors to invalidate surfaces. Clients are
    required to submit a new buffer after the compositor invalidates a surface.
    Compositors might take advantage of this protocol to recover from GPU
    resets.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_surface_invalidation_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="surface invalidation manager">
      A factory interface to create surface invalidation objects.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="1"
        summary="a surface invalidation object has already been constructed"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the wp_surface_invalidation_manager_v1 object.

        The child objects created via this interface are unaffected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_surface_invalidation">
      <description summary="extend surface interface for invalidation">
        Create a wl_surface extension for invalidation.

        Clients must create at most one wp_surface_invalidation_v1 per
        wl_surface object, otherwise the already_constructed protocol
        error is sent.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_surface_invalidation_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_surface_invalidation_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="surface invalidation">
      An add-on interface for wl_surface to handle invalidation events.

      Creating this object signals to the compositor that the client
      supports invalidation events on this surface.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="unresponsive" value="1"
        summary="client didn't ack an invalidated event in time"/>
      <entry name="invalid_serial" value="2"
        summary="client acked an invalid serial"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="invalidated">
      <description summary="surface has been invalidated">
        Sent by the compositor when the surface has been invalidated.

        The client is required to handle the invalidated event by
        attaching a new buffer on the surface, sending an ack request
        with the same serial as the event, and then committing the
        surface.

        A compositor may raise an unresponsive protocol error to clients
        that does not acknowledge an invalidation event in time. The
        timeout used is up to the compositor.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="invalidation serial"/>
    </event>

    <request name="ack">
      <description summary="acknowledge surface invalidation">
        Acknowledge a surface invalidation event.

        This event must be paired with a request to attach a new buffer
        on the surface, and needs to be followed by a surface commit to
        be applied.

        If the serial doesn't match a previous invalidated event, or if
        the same serial is acked twice, the invalid_serial protocol
        error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="invalidation serial"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the surface invalidation object">
        Destroy the surface invalidation object.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
