<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="transactions_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020      Red Hat Inc.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="wp_transaction_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="surface group transactions">
      This interface offers ways to make multiple surfaces commit atomically,
      instead of each surface by themself. It works simimarly to how subsurface
      state synhronization in that the state committed by a wl_surface.commit is
      cached compositor side, then later applied to the active surface state at
      a later point.

      It can be used either as a replacement for subsurface synchronization, or
      for example synchronize a popup surface with its parent, or a transient
      dialog with its parent.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="unbind the transaction factory">
	Destroy the wp_transaction_manager_v1 object. Objects created through
	this interface will remain valid.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create_transaction">
      <description summary="create a new transaction object">
	Create a new one time transaction object. A transaction object can be
	used once to group multiple surfaces together making all their committed
	state being applied atomically at the same time.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_transaction_v1"
	   summary="the new transaction object"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_transaction_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="transaction object">
      This objects represent a surface group that will always be atomically
      applied together. Clients can add surfaces with
      wp_transaction_v1.add_surface.

      When surfaces that have been added to a wp_transaction_v1 object request
      wl_surface.commit, the pending state will be cached by the compositor.
      When the state of all the surfaces that should be updated together has
      been committed, the client can request wp_transaction_v1.commit to apply
      all the surfaces state in one go.

      After a transaction object is committed, it becomes defunct and cannot be
      reused.

      When an added surface is a synchronized subsurface, the state that is
      cached is not the state committed using wl_surface.commit but the state
      that is effectively applied as defined by the wl_subsurface protocol. Thus
      for a synchronized subsurface to have its state to be applied to the
      active state of the surface, while also added to a wp_transaction_v1
      object, the state must first be applied according to the subsurface
      protocol, at which point it will be cached as part of the
      wp_transaction_v1 object, then committed using wp_transaction_v1.commit.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_used" value="0"
	     summary="the surface already belongs to another transaction object"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="add_surface">
      <description summary="add a surface to the transaction object">
	Add a surface to the transaction object. After a surface has been added,
	all pending state committed using wl_surface.commit will be cached until
	wp_transaction_v1.commit is called.

	A surface can only be added to one transaction object at a time. If
	added while already belonging to some transaction object, an
	'already_used' error will be raised.

	If a surface added to a transaction object is destroyed, it's cached
	state is dropped as well, and the wp_transaction_v1 object will behave as
	if the surface was never added.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit" type="destructor">
      <description summary="commit all the cached surface states">
	Commit all the state that has been committed and cached by the surfaces
	in the wp_transaction_v1 object. This request has no effect on any
	pending wl_surface state.

	This will also destroy the wp_transaction_v1 object.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

</protocol>
