<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xx_pip_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Vlad Zahorodnii

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="xx_pip_shell_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="create picture-in-picture surfaces">
      The xx_pip_shell_v1 interface provides a way to create picture-in-picture
      windows.

      Use cases are for example playing a video in a separate floating window.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="role" value="0" summary="given wl_surface has another role"/>
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="1" summary="wl_surface has a buffer attached or committed"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy xx_pip_shell_v1">
        Destroy this xx_pip_shell_v1 object. Objects that have been created
        through this instance are unaffected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_pip">
      <description summary="create picture-in-picture surface from a surface">
        This creates an xx_pip_v1 for the given xdg_surface and gives the
        associated wl_surface the xx_pip_v1 role.

        If the wl_surface already has a role assigned, a role protocol error
        will be raised.

        Creating a picture-in-picture surface from a wl_surface which has a
        buffer attached or committed is a client error, and any attempts by
        a client to attach or manipulate a buffer prior to the first
        xx_pip_v1.configure event must also be treated as errors.

        After creating an xx_pip_v1 object and setting it up, the client
        must perform an initial commit without any buffer attached.
        The compositor will reply with a xx_pip_v1.configure event.
        The client must acknowledge it and is then allowed to attach a buffer
        to map the surface.

        The compositor may deny showing the picture-in-picture surface, in
        which case it will send the closed event before the first configure
        event.

        See the documentation of xdg_surface for more details about what an
        xdg_surface is and how it is used.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xx_pip_v1"/>
      <arg name="xdg_surface" type="object" interface="xdg_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xx_pip_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="picture-in-picture surface">
      This interface defines an xdg_surface role which represents a floating
      window with some miniature contents, for example a video.

      The picture-in-picture window will be placed above all other windows.
      Compositor-specific policies may override or customize the behavior
      and the placement of the xx_pip_v1. For example, the compositor may
      choose to put the xx_pip_v1 in a screen corner, etc.

      Unmapping an xx_pip_v1 means that the surface cannot be shown
      by the compositor until it is explicitly mapped again.
      All active operations (e.g., move, resize) are canceled and all
      attributes (e.g. title, state, stacking, ...) are discarded for
      an xx_pip_v1 surface when it is unmapped. The xx_pip_v1 returns to
      the state it had right after xx_pip_shell_v1.get_pip. The client
      can re-map the pip by perfoming a commit without any buffer
      attached, waiting for a configure event and handling it as usual (see
      xdg_surface description).

      Attaching a null buffer to a picture-in-picture unmaps the surface.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_size" value="0" summary="invalid surface size provided"/>
      <entry name="invalid_origin" value="1" summary="invalid origin"/>
      <entry name="invalid_resize_edge" value="2" summary="invalid resize edge"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the xx_pip_v1">
        This request destroys the role surface and unmaps the surface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_app_id">
      <description summary="set application ID">
        Set an application identifier for the surface.

        The app ID identifies the general class of applications to which
        the surface belongs. The compositor can use this to group multiple
        surfaces together, or to determine how to launch a new application.

        For D-Bus activatable applications, the app ID is used as the D-Bus
        service name.

        The compositor shell will try to group application surfaces together
        by their app ID. As a best practice, it is suggested to select app
        ID's that match the basename of the application's .desktop file.
        For example, "org.freedesktop.FooViewer" where the .desktop file is
        "org.freedesktop.FooViewer.desktop".

        Like other properties, a set_app_id request can be sent after the
        xx_pip_v1 has been mapped to update the property.

        See the desktop-entry specification [0] for more details on
        application identifiers and how they relate to well-known D-Bus
        names and .desktop files.

        [0] http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/
      </description>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_origin">
      <description summary="set origin surface">
        Set the origin surface for the picture-in-picture surface.

        The origin surface is an optional property that specifies a surface
        from which the picture-in-picture surface has been launched. If set,
        the compositor may use this hint to play an animation when the
        picture-in-picture surface is mapped or unmapped. For example, smoothly
        move the surface from the origin to a screen corner.

        If the specified origin surface is the same as the picture-in-picture
        surface, the invalid_origin protocol error will be posted.

        The origin surface is double-buffered state, see wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="origin" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_origin_rect">
      <description summary="set origin rect">
        Set the origin rect within the origin surface for the picture-in-picture
        surface.

        The origin rect is an optional property that specifies the launch
        rectangle within the origin surface. The compositor may use this hint
        to play an animation when the picture-in-picture surface is mapped or
        unmapped. For example, smoothly move the surface from the origin rect
        to a screen corner.

        The origin rect is specified in the surface-local coordinate space.

        The compositor ignores the parts of the origin rect that fall outside
        of the origin surface.

        The origin rect is double-buffered state, see wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="move">
      <description summary="start an interactive move">
        Start an interactive, user-driven move of the surface.

        This request must be used in response to some sort of user action
        like a button press, key press, or touch down event. The passed
        serial is used to determine the type of interactive move (touch,
        pointer, etc).

        The server may ignore move requests depending on the state of
        the surface, or if the passed serial is no longer valid.

        If triggered, the surface will lose the focus of the device
        (wl_pointer, wl_touch, etc) used for the move. It is up to the
        compositor to visually indicate that the move is taking place, such as
        updating a pointer cursor, during the move. There is no guarantee
        that the device focus will return when the move is completed.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat of the user event"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="resize_edge">
      <description summary="edge values for resizing">
        These values are used to indicate which edge of a surface
        is being dragged in a resize operation.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0"/>
      <entry name="top" value="1"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="2"/>
      <entry name="left" value="4"/>
      <entry name="top_left" value="5"/>
      <entry name="bottom_left" value="6"/>
      <entry name="right" value="8"/>
      <entry name="top_right" value="9"/>
      <entry name="bottom_right" value="10"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="resize">
      <description summary="start an interactive resize">
        Start a user-driven, interactive resize of the surface.

        This request must be used in response to some sort of user action
        like a button press, key press, or touch down event. The passed
        serial is used to determine the type of interactive resize (touch,
        pointer, etc).

        The server may ignore resize requests depending on the state of
        the surface, or if the passed serial is no longer valid.

        If triggered, the surface also will lose the focus of the device
        (wl_pointer, wl_touch, etc) used for the resize. It is up to the
        compositor to visually indicate that the resize is taking place,
        such as updating a pointer cursor, during the resize. There is no
        guarantee that the device focus will return when the resize is
        completed.

        The edges parameter specifies how the surface should be resized,
        and is one of the values of the resize_edge enum. The compositor
        may use this information to update the surface position for
        example when dragging the top left corner. The compositor may also
        use this information to adapt its behavior, e.g. choose an
        appropriate cursor image.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat of the user event"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
      <arg name="edges" type="uint" enum="resize_edge" summary="which edge or corner is being dragged"/>
    </request>

    <event name="closed">
      <description summary="picture-in-picture surface has been closed">
        The closed event is sent by the compositor when the surface will
        no longer be shown. Further changes to the surface will be ignored.
        The client should destroy the resource after receiving this event.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="configure_bounds">
      <description summary="surface bounds">
        The configure_bounds event may be sent prior to a xx_pip_v1.configure
        event to communicate the bounds a surface size must be constrained to.

        The passed width and height are in surface coordinate space.

        If the surface width or the surface height is greater than the specified
        surface size bounds, an invalid_size protocol error will be posted.

        The surface bounds subject to compositor policies.

        The bounds may change at any point, and in such a case, a new
        xx_pip_v1.configure_bounds will be sent, followed by xx_pip_v1.configure and
        xdg_surface.configure.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <event name="configure_size">
      <description summary="suggest a surface change">
        This configure event asks the client to resize its pip surface.
        The configured state should not be applied immediately. See
        xdg_surface.configure for details.

        The width and height arguments specify a hint to the window
        about how its surface should be resized in window geometry
        coordinates. See set_window_geometry.

        If the width or height arguments are zero, it means the client
        should decide its own window dimension.

        Clients must send an ack_configure in response to this event. See
        xdg_surface.configure and xdg_surface.ack_configure for details.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
